<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<document>

	<properties>
		<title>
			Configure GWT Tomcat Lite Instance (if not using gwt-maven)
		</title>
	</properties>

	<body>
		<section
			name="Configure GWT Tomcat Lite Instance (if not using gwt-maven)">
			
			<subsection
				name="How to configure Hosted Mode Tomcat Lite">
				<p>
					If you do not use Maven and are not using the
					gwt-maven plugin then you can still manipulate the GWT embedded Tomcat Lite instance.
					You will simply need to configure things manually.
					<br /><br />
					(If you DO use the plugin, which is recommended -
					just setup your project like the <a href="sample.html">sample</a> - then all
					of this is done FOR you automatically, using the
					Maven properties.)
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Understanding the MUNGING approach">
				<p>
					First up understand that to get things working with
					regard to GWT and the embedded Tomcat Lite instance, 
					with projects that require resources
					such as DataSources in Hosted Mode (from context.xml
					and web.xml), there are several ways to approach it. 
					This way, what the plugin ultimately does, munging the embedded Tomcat configuration,
					is only one approach.
					<br />
					<br />
					The MUNGE approach to configuring the Hosted Mode Tomcat
					Lite instance allows you to include the resources to
					run your project in hosted mode - these are
					typically a context descriptor (context.xml) a
					deployment descriptor (web.xml) and dependencies
					(JDBC drivers and so on).
				</p>
				<p>
					Alternative techniques include using an <a href="configure_noserver.html">external container instance</a>.
					and or using MOCK objects while working in Hosted
					Mode. All of these techniques (munge, externalize,
					mock) are viable and have pros and cons.
				</p>
				</subsection>
				<subsection name="Taking the MUNGING approach">
				<p>
					Manipulating the GWT embeded Hosted	Mode Tomcat instance, "Tomcat Lite."
				</p>
				<p>
				<b>Context.xml</b>
				<br />
					1. Put <a
						href="http://gwt-maven.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/maven-googlewebtoolkit-sample/web/META-INF/context.xml">
						context.xml
					</a> where it needs to be:
					<code>[PROJECT]/tomcat/conf/gwt/localhost/ROOT.xml</code>.
				</p>
				<p>
					Rename context.xml to ROOT.xml and place it in
					[PROJECT]/tomcat/conf/gwt/localhost.
				</p>
				<p>
					Also be aware that as of today (GWT version 1.2.22)
					the Hosted Mode "Tomcat Lite" is Tomcat version
					5.0.28. This means you need to use the long form for
					defining resources within context.xml (this form
					changed in Tomcat 5.5.x - see the sample for how it
					works on 5.0.x).
				</p>
				<p>
				<b>web.xml</b>
				<br />
					2. Put <a
						href="http://gwt-maven.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/maven-googlewebtoolkit-sample/web/WEB-INF/web.xml">
						web.xml
					</a> where it needs to be:
					<code>[PROJECT]/tomcat/webapps/ROOT/WEB-INF/web.xml</code>.
				</p>
				<p>
					Pretty self explanatory there, same name, goes in
					[PROJECT]/tomcat/webapps/ROOT/WEB-INF.
				</p>
				<p>
				<b>Dependencies</b>
				<br />
					3. Include dependencies your setup needs ON the
					classpath when you start GWTShell.
				</p>
				<p>
					The Tomcat Lite provided with GWT does not have
					commons-pool or commons-dbcp and so on. Whatever you
					need with your project needs to be supplied on the
					classpath when starting GWTShell. Take a look at a
					simple MyProject-shell script (what
					ApplicationCreator creates) and you will see how the
					shell is invoked and what is included on the
					classpath, edit that (or provide an env var, or so
					on) to manipulate the classpath as needed.
					<br />
					<br />
					The sample includes dependencies through the plugin
					creating the classpath, based on the maven
					dependencies, before it invokes the shell (the
					sample will not help you if you are not using maven
					and the plugin).
				</p>
			</subsection>

		</section>
	</body>
</document>